Well, now that we have the basic game mechanics working for both of the sprites, it's time to make
it all work together by checking if the ball is touching the player's head and then bouncing back if
it does.
But before I go ahead and sort out this, there are two things I want to fix with the player.
The first is getting the player to appear further down so that we have more space, and the second is
switching to a more appropriate costume.
I bet you can figure out how to do both of these.
Come on, let's pause the video and figure it out.
The first thing is to click on our player sprite so we can get it to appear lower down.
Now I could just drag it like this, but this isn't ideal because if I move it again by accident, the
whole thing won't work properly.
So instead what I'll do is bring in this go to block and change the X to zero, and let's make the Y
- 90.
That actually looks perfect.
So let's add this to the start of our script.
So now every time our script will start in the correct position.
Then lastly, to get our character looking correct in this game, we can go into the costumes and change
it to this one Ben see which works much better.
Now we need to get the ball to respond to our main character.
So click on the ball sprite.
Now let's think about it.
Basically, what we want to happen is to have the ball bounce off the player's head.
What specific instructions or code do we need to write in order to achieve this?
Well, this problem also has to do with sensing as we are sensing if the ball is touching our player.
So we know we are going to have our basic code blocks for this which are listed.
Before I remind you, the basic code blocks the when start the forever and the if.
And just like our dragonfly, we're going to need this touching code.
And here we can change it to sense if it's touching.
Ben.
Okay, cool.
So we now know if the ball is touching Ben.
Now what can we do to get it to bounce if it touches Ben?
You'll notice that there is unfortunately no bounce if touching the main character block, which would
be really cool.
But remember, with code there is never going to be a single block that does this.
It's all about combining code and building scripts to achieve this.
And this is really the great thing which you'll see in future lessons.
This is programming, and what you can do is you can save these scripts and use them in different programs.
So maybe in a different program, we need a script that bounces off another sprite.
And once we create the script, we can reuse it forever.
And this is an important concept in coding.
It's called reusable code and it saves a lot of time.
But getting back on topic.
Let's move to the motions group.
Now remember how we are using this move code block.
And what is special about this is how the direction the ball moves is dependent on the direction it's
facing.
So simply to get our ball to bounce up, all we need to do is face it in an upwards direction.
And to do this, all we need to do is bring in this point in the direction block.
But right now you can see it is trying to point 90 degrees, which is to the right.
But if we click on this note, what brings up this little arrow thing?
Not going?
So for our code, we want the ball to go up so we can face the arrow up, which is zero degrees.
Now, if we play our code, you'll see that when we touch the ball, it bounces up.
Perfect.
Although as you can see, it's kind of just goes up and down and up and down, which is making it a
very easy game.
But in the next lesson, we'll see how we can make this game a bit more challenging and a lot more fun
with randomness.